Hello and welcome to Useful Idiots. I'm
Katie Halper.
>> I'm Aaron Mate. Thanks so much for being
here. Our website, as always, is
usefulodcast.com.
Today we have a double header for you.
Uh yet again, we're going to be covering
of course uh the non-event that was the
Epstein Files. the Trump administration
claiming after basically so many months
and years of hyping up the Epstein files
this week saying actually nothing to see
here. Well, former CIA officer John
Keryaku will be here to give uh his take
on what's going on.
>> It's always fascinating talking to John.
and he has amazing stories and also uh
it should be known people may be
interested in knowing that uh John is
the only person to spend any time in
prison over the uh CIA's torture
program. Uh this is a program in which
he did not participate but he blew the
whistle on it. So of course uh in the
United States you don't ever get in
trouble for committing crimes, you get
in trouble for exposing them. Well,
speaking of exposing crimes, in the
second half of the show, we'll also hear
from Marta Havrisko. Uh she is a
returning guest. She is a visiting
assistant professor at Clark University
and she's Ukrainian and she's very
critical of the Ukrainian government,
also very critical of the Russian
government. Um, but what she has to say
about Ukraine contradicts a lot of the
narratives we get here in the West uh
that is used to sustain the proxy war
there, which a lot of people have kind
of forgotten about because it's been
going on for so long and there's so many
other horrible crises in the world,
namely the genocide in Gaza. But
Ukraine's still happening and as we'll
hear in today's interview with Marta,
things are very bleak.
>> What else is bleak is uh the news here,
the news there. And I guess that's a
great transition to uh start the four
basic food groups. Uh, Democrats suck.
Republicans suck. Isn't that weird?
Isn't that terrible? What bleak news do
we have from Democrats suck?
>> Well, the main source of bleakness right
now for Democrats is this light onto New
York City, onto the big apple, uh, Zoran
Mani, his successful campaign in the
Democratic uh, primary for mayor and how
are corporate Democrats grappling with
the fact that this charismatic, young
challenger is set to become the next
mayor of New York City on the Democratic
ticket? Well, they're handling this by
saying he's not welcome inside their
party. As former Biden challenger Dean
Phillips just told CNN,
>> "Is there room for you and Mandani in
the Democratic party?"
>> You know, I think it's a it's a fine
question. I think it's one that many
Republicans have been asking about
whether there's room for traditional
conservatives in a party now led by mega
Republicans like Donald Trump. Uh the
answer ultimately, I think, is no. You
know, we do share many of the same
values. In fact,
>> great. Can you can you leave the party,
Dean? Dean Phillips, can we get that in
writing? That would be great. Please
retire right now.
>> Most Americans share a lot of the same
values. But as a political party, yes,
you want diversity. You want some
differences of opinion, perspective,
life story, politics, and experience.
But when you have socialists, when you
have socialists in the Democratic party,
uh I don't know how anybody could argue
that that would be beneficial for the
party or for the country. There in lies
the great challenge. Same thing on the
right, Omar. Uh is MAGA the future of
the Republican party? If it is, there is
going to be a new grand successful third
party in America because the
overwhelming majority of Americans want
neither far-left or far-right politics.
They want decency. They want common
sense, competency, and cooperation. And
no party right now is elevating
candidates who represent those ideals.
>> Decency, competence, and cooperation,
and common sense. All right. Decency,
cooperation, common sense. Cooperation,
common sense, competency. I think he's
maybe starting his own third party, the
the triple C party.
>> The DEC.
Yes. Decency, competency,
>> cooperation, and what was the last one?
It already felt it already escaped me.
That's how uh meaningful it is.
>> He's basically saying that everybody
wants a centrist corporate Democrat.
That's what he's basically saying.
That's his that he's still clinging to.
And it's not a question of like if the
Republican party is now MAGA. They are
like MAGA. And that's the base of the
party now. So it's it's not as if
there's like a bunch of Republicans
dying to leave. there's like a small
sliver of like I don't know uh I guess
you want to call like old school
Republicans who don't like Donald Trump
but like
>> right
>> Republicans are MAGA and look he says we
want diversity of opinion to the
Democratic party and diversity of
background but you can't have a
socialist but in Zora Mandani's case
like what does that mean to be a
socialist basically he he supports
universal healthcare universal prek he
wants to have free buses for people he
wants to have government subsidized
grocery stores so that in some
communities where there are no healthy
food options or or barely any food
options at all that you have ways to
serve people so that people can be fed.
>> Um these aren't radical policies
actually that he is pursuing. And of
course he also wants a rent freeze which
is also not socialist. It's just kind of
trying to basically make the city
affordable for working people.
>> Right. I wonder what Dean Phillips
thinks of like FDR if he thought he was
a big scary socialist who should have
been banned from the Democratic party.
Although I do think they're genuinely
alarmed by Zoramani's progressive
policies. I think another issue is the
fact that he sees Palestinians as equal
human beings, right?
>> And the Democrats have played this game
where that's just simply not allowed, at
least in the leadership of the party. If
you want to run for president, if you
want to be a Senate or House leader, you
have to bow down to Israel. And now you
have the potential next mayor of New
York City not playing that game. And
that also to them is not welcome,
>> right? And I think they're afraid of
saying that, right? Because the irony is
that these Zionists are really messed up
because I think that they helped Zoron
Mam Donnie because they kind of tried to
make this a referendum on Israel and I
think a lot of people were disgusted by
it because it just seems so irrelevant
and so forced. I mean it's you do do
certain things as the mayor of New York
related to um foreign policy. um there's
some symbolic things. Um they're like,
you know, agreements with a with foreign
governments and stuff, but I think they
were so over the top that it backfired.
And so now I think that the Democrats
realize if they try to vilify Zoron over
Palestine, they're just going to make
him all the more popular probably. So,
as Dean Phillips is basically saying
that Zoraman is not welcome inside his
party, uh Joe Scarro of MSNBC
asks a uh a very good question like why
is it that corporate Democrats like Dean
Phillips can't reach anybody whereas
Zoran Mani can? Now, this is Joe
Scarbor. And why is it that in the
Democratic party the three most
compelling figures uh the the Maril
candidate uh Bernie Sanders and AOC uh
the three most compelling figures since
the election have been uh far left of
let's say the mainstream of of a lot of
Americans. Um, why why why can't
moderate Democrats why can't
conservative moderate Democrats like you
uh make that same compelling message?
>> Geez, I don't know, Joe. Maybe because
they have no message. Yeah.
>> And people are tired of it and they have
nothing to offer anyone anymore except
like, I don't know, worshiping Israel
and not being as ghoulish on some issues
as Republicans. For example, corporate
Democrats are to their credit not
supporting Medicaid cuts, which which is
great, but people want more than that.
And in Zora Mandani and Bernie Sanders
and AOC, you have people who champion
workers and who actually have like
concrete policies that they're willing
to fight for. Maybe that's why the the
so-called moderates can't reach anybody.
>> Well, yeah. And it's interesting because
I think you know uh it's very revealing
that Scarboro presents uh Bernie AOC and
Mom Donnie as far from the mainstream
because something that Bernie really
helped show the world is that these
things that are called radical are
radical and fringe among the elites but
not among people. So there's nothing
actually radical um in the idea of
having to not die because you don't have
enough money. Well, another issue that
corporate Democrats face is that people
rightly don't see them as having any
real convictions and that they'll just
say whatever. A good example of this is
Chuck Schumer who made a lot of noise
when he stood up in Congress and gave a
speech basically denouncing Benjamin
Netanyahu and saying that he has to go,
right? And this was supposed to be some
huge shift from Chuck Schumer who's a
lifelong defender of the Israeli
government. Well, Benjamin Netanyahu
just visited Washington. And guess who
is posing in a picture with Benjamin
Netanyahu? None other than Chuck
Schumer. Here he is. There's Chuck
Schumer alongside some Republican
colleagues with Benjamin Netanyahu. The
same guy who Chuck Schumer said, you
know, has to go because he's so awful
for Israel and you know, this is not who
Israel is. Well, Chuck Schumer is
someone who's willing to pose with the
guy who he called on to resign,
>> right? which which is of course on top
of the fact that Chuck Schumer is like a
you know a complete uh is totally
subservient to Israel,
>> he also just doesn't have any principles
that he's willing to stick to.
>> Yeah. But Aaron, look at him. He is
boldly boldly looking away. He's not
looking at the camera and that is his
way of registering his resistance.
>> Yeah. Well, uh I he probably is probably
thinks exactly that.
>> Yeah,
>> that's probably what he wants to think.
But I'm sorry. Don't pose in the back if
you want him to resign.
>> Right. True. Very true. Yeah. For
Republican suck, we have an adorable
kind of suite of developments. Um people
may remember that back in May, Trump
announced he would be lifting sanctions
um from Syria. And uh in his executive
order on the matter from the end of
June, he also declared he would take
Hayat Tar al-Sham, HDS, which is al
Qaeda's uh former affiliate in Syria.
that was led by Abu Muhammad Al Jalani,
now the leader of Syria, um off the
designated foreign terrorist list. Now,
here is a video of Trump from this week
at a dinner he hosted for Netanyahu and
the Israeli delegation. And listen to
him talking about this decision. you
know the at the request of a lot of
countries in the surrounding area of the
Middle East including BB uh we will uh
we took the sanctions off Syria and I
met the new leader I was very impressed
by him and somebody said well he comes
from a very tough background I said well
you know I'm not that surprised it's a
tough part of the world
>> so Aaron I I want to pass it to you as
someone who's really studied a lot
researched a lot and written a lot about
um Syria and HDS uh anything you want to
share about this tough guy?
>> Well, yeah, he's the founding leader of
al-Qaeda and Syria and a former deputy
leader of ISIS and they were responsible
for not only, you know, attacking US
soldiers, which Trump and other neocons
want to forget about now, but also
sectarian killings in Syria, which are
still ongoing under Galani's watch. In
fact, Reuters recently did an
investigation about how the slaughter of
more than a thousand Alawite civilians
after regime change in Syria last year
uh was linked to forces under Galani's
control. But now that Syria uh is
basically in the pocket of the US and
Israel because they overthrew a
government that was in the axis of
resistance um and there's talk of Syria
and Israel reaching some sort of
normalization agreement or some sort of
tacid agreement. basically Syria no
longer being a part of the block that
resists Israel. Now we can say that this
guy Al Jalani, the former leader of
al-Qaeda in Syria is uh yeah, great guy.
He's tough, you know, and let's remove
sanctions on his government,
>> right? Uh so they're removing sanctions
on his government. They're also removing
the terrorist designation from uh his
organization. But guys, this makes a lot
of sense because uh the Trump
administration and Marco Rubio in
particular have decided to focus on a
much worse villain, a much bigger
threat, a much bigger terrorist. And
they are in fact imposing sanctions on
this terrorist. Uh we actually full uh
transparency we once interviewed this
terrorist and this terrorist is UN Human
Rights Council special reperator
Francesca Albanz. Uh and let's take a
look at this uh announcement from Rubio.
Today I'm imposing sanctions on UN Human
Rights Council special reperator
Franchesca Albanz for her illegitimate
and shameful efforts to prompt the
International Criminal Court to take
action against US and Israeli officials,
companies and executives.
Uh, Albanese's campaign of political and
economic warfare against the United
States and Israel will no longer be
tolerated. We will always stand by our
partners in their right to self-defense.
The United States will continue to take
whatever action we deem necessary to
respond to lawfare and protect our
sovereignty and that of our allies. So
just to review, uh the person who we are
sanctioning is someone who opposes
genocide and who had the uh tmerity to
lay out in an excellent report the way
that different companies are complicit
in genocide. But the person who uh
commits war crimes gets to have
sanctions lifted off of his country and
gets to have his organization uh
welcomed into the non-terrorist world.
So that kind of uh says everything you
need to know about the rank hypocrisy of
the United States.
>> And someone to show the contrast in in
really uh simple terms is Trita Pary. He
uh wrote this. The man below is the
founder of al-Qaeda and Syria. The US
just took his organization off its
terror list and lifted sanctions on him.
The woman below is the UN rapper on
Israel and Palestine. The US is about to
impose sanctions on her. Let that sink
in. Yes. And I hope people can now who
maybe were confused by the war in Syria,
who heard maybe nasty things about the
stance that people like me took. I hope
that this contrast can help you
understand why some of us were opposed
to regime change in Syria. This was
never about bringing freedom and
democracy to Syria. Uh this was about
just basically destabilizing a country
that was part of a resistance block to
Israel. That's what the dirty war in
Syria was for. exploiting internal
divisions, exploiting legitimate
grievances inside a country to fuel a
humanitarian catastrophe and ultimately
support an insurgency that was led by
al-Qaeda and that's who now takes power.
And because the government now in power
will essentially not challenge the US
and Israel in the region, then their
sanctions can be removed. And someone
like Franchesca Albanesei who challenges
Israel simply by trying to apply the law
to Israel, she has sanctions on her. So
that contrast is really important to
understand not only how just what a
fallacy the so-called rules-based
international order is. Uh exposing just
how subservient
uh international institutions and
governments are to Israel, but also just
the aims behind our regime change
awards. It's always to advance hegemony.
It's never to advance human rights and
freedom. really uh want to give a shout
out to uh Francesca
uh for being so fearless despite the
fact that she's not only smeared as an
anti-semite, which is a totally baseless
accusation, but um uh now she's being
sanctioned by the United States. The
world of fast fashion has complicated
clothing production by shipping cheap
parts around the world to whoever can
sew them the cheapest. And now you're
paying the price with rising costs and
tariffs. Back in the 1960s, 95% of
clothing Americans bought were made in
the USA. Today, it's only 3%. That's why
we like American Giant. American Giant
is Americanmade, producing their clothes
locally and giving back to the
communities that support them. At a time
when fast fashion is dominating the
fashion space, it's nice to feel good
about what we wear. American Giant is
about durable, not disposable products.
They make clothes built to last. So,
buying from American Giant is an
investment, not just in clothes, but in
a community trying to do things the
right way. Support Americanmade
terror-free clothing with American
Giant. Get 20% off your first order when
you use promo code useful at
american-giant.com.
That's 20% off when you use code useful
at american-giant.com.
What do we got for Isn't that weird?
>> For Isn't that weird? Let's turn to
a look back at the Kla Harris campaign.
And you know, it's worth recalling that
Kla Harris had the opportunity to
distance herself from Joe Biden,
especially on the issue of the Gaza
genocide, which made it so hard for so
many people to vote for Democrats as
much as they feared the Donald Trump
campaign. Well, Kla Harris uh was not
willing to distance herself from Joe
Biden and just was overall not very good
at this campaigning thing. And we got a
new anecdote about this from Kareem
Rakma. He is the host of the very
popular social media uh account Subway
Takes where he interviews basically
people on the New York City subway or
foreign subways too and asked for their
take. And so he just revealed that right
before the vote in the US presidential
election last year, Kla Harris did a
subway take. But Kla Harris was so bad
that both parties decided it wasn't
worth airing. So this is what Karim
Rakma said about Kla Harris's ill- fated
appearance on Subway Tix.
>> They emailed me.
>> They emailed they get an email from the
>> the DNC.
>> Okay.
>> And they said, "Hey, Kla Harris and Tim
Walls are really interested in being on
your show." I said, "That sounds cool.
I'll at least get to tell my daughter
that I met
>> the potential president of the United
States." And so I said yes. based on on
the fact that it would be a good story
and also they both had good takes.
>> What happened with Kamla?
>> Her take was really confusing and weird
and not good and so mutually agreed that
uh we shouldn't publish it.
>> I see.
>> And I got lucky because I didn't want to
be blamed for her losing.
>> Her take was that bad?
>> It was really really bad and it was inc
It was like didn't make any sense. I can
tell you bacon bacon is a spice.
>> Bacon is a spice.
>> So Kla Harris's take right before a
presidential election was that bacon is
a spice. And come on. Like I mean
staffers like I don't even blame Kla
Harris for this. Like staffers for this
reason. Some people workshop this. They
come up with the best take. And
especially before an election you want
to like I understand they were probably
thinking it would show her more, you
know, her human side if they did
something non-political. But come on,
get your message out. Instead, they went
with bacon as a spice. And yeah, it was
so bad that uh they canceled themselves
and they, you know, yet another
opportunity for Kla Harris was
squandered.
>> I mean, you know, you would have thought
that that she would have learned her
lesson from um spice related commentary
from when Hillary Clinton said that she
kept hot sauce in her purse.
>> That's a great point. That was so phony
when Hillary Clinton claimed that like
she was asked like what like what's the
one thing you bring uh around uh with
you everywhere and she was like well hot
sauce in my bag and it was such a I
don't know what they I think the thought
there was like they would reach
African-American voters with that right
that was the idea behind that.
>> It was just so condescending and phony
and
>> yeah no wonder that was a loser. So yes,
exact. You're so right, Kla. It's like
they adopted one of the dumbest Hillary
Clinton tactics, losing Hillary Clinton
tactics.
>> Oh my god,
>> it's just it's all the ineptitude of the
Democrats just it never ceases to amaze.
It really doesn't. It really does. And
now we're living with the consequences.
Like, and I don't want to I don't want
to downplay the differences between the
two parties because Republicans now, we
just saw this with their so-called big
beautiful bill, which is such a
monstrosity. It's like, it's so awful.
They're increasing the Pentagon budget.
They're cutting taxes for the ultra
wealthy. They're taking away Medicaid
and food stamps from millions of
vulnerable people. And Democrats, for
all their faults, wouldn't have done
something so ghoullish. They wouldn't.
They wouldn't. And it's important to
recognize that difference. But Democrats
just made it so hard to vote for them.
And we continue to get new reminders as
to how that they couldn't even do a
proper subway tick.
>> Yeah, they really they did not make it
easy. I mean, speaking of Clinton call
backs, I mean, remember they had Bill
Clinton uh address a crowd in in
Michigan. And you know, this isn't the
Bill Clinton of like 15 years ago. He
used to be a very good panderer, but
he's kind of lost the art. Um, and so he
wasn't able to pander at all. He just
came off as incredibly offensive, which
he is, but he used to be better at
hiding it. You got to know when you've
lost your your gift. Yeah. And of
course, I'm referring to uh Bill Clinton
basically arguing that uh Jews have a
theological uh justification for being
in Israel.
>> Yeah. Great job, Democrats, sending that
message to Michigan, you know,
>> home to the country's largest uh
ArabAmerican uh population. Uh really
wonderful job. Thank you. Thank you,
Democrats, for that.
>> So, for Isn't that terrible? Uh, let's
take a listen to someone who we haven't
covered in a while on this show. In
fact, Aaron, I think we haven't covered
him since you've joined. Um, but the
lovely right-wing commentator Charlie
Kirk, uh, this week during an episode of
his aonomous show on the farright
network, Real America's Voice, he made
some pretty interesting comments about,
uh, where to lay the blame for uh, the
at least tw the at least 120 deaths that
occurred uh, when flash floods struck
Texas. Let's hear what he has to say.
>> The Democrats, they're so despicable.
The Democrats are not lifting a finger
to remember the well over 100 people
that have died in Texas Hill Country.
What you are not being told by the media
anywhere
is that the death toll likely would not
have been as high if it wasn't for DEI.
This Texas tragedy is just the latest
example.
It's not just incompetence.
This is DEI working to undermine
meritocratic institutions
and more people likely died than
otherwise would have because of DEI.
>> Okay, so basically he's saying uh too
many people of color have jobs uh and
that's why all these people died in
flash floods. Um, it is so disgusting
and it's so evidence-free and it's a
good reminder good speaking of callbacks
uh to when Elon Musk and former Fox News
host Megan Kelly and others tried to
blame uh the LA fires on DEI. Now,
what's great about these claims is they
don't feel any pressure to provide any
evidence. It's just such an obvious uh
deflection. It also is a deflection from
uh what really is the cause and that is
climate change denial uh austerity
measures and uh those are are
implemented in many cases to finance the
rich through tax cuts and also give uh
big oil handouts and subsidies but again
no proof whatsoever that DI had anything
to do with it and we don't know the
exact culprit yet but it is um important
to remember that uh certain things were
done that cannot have been uh helpful
that are very dangerous uh in
themselves. So uh key positions have
been cut as a result of Trump's Doge
cuts including a warning coordination
meteorologist position which helps
coordinate evacuations with weather
forecasters and emergency managers and
the public. They many are saying that
while there were cuts, it wasn't
understaffed at the time of the floods,
but experts have noted that these key
vacancies could have played a role. Um,
and of course, uh, the N OAA's new
budget as a result of Trump's cuts under
his one big beautiful bill would now
essentially close all NAA labs,
including the lab with uh, a key tool
for predicting klutz.
>> Everyone has their boogeyman. Democrats
for a long time blamed Russia for
everything. The MAGA people have have
many book I mean they like to blame many
different sources undocumented
immigrants but certainly every single
disaster you can always blame DEI.
>> Yeah. And you know again there is more
much to be uh investigated and
demonstrated but obviously it's not good
to to cut these positions to cut funding
for things like this. And it more
generally like warmer temperatures
increase the amount of water vapor held
by clouds which allows for more uh
torrential downpours. And that's that's
just established fact.
>> And those have been your four basic food
groups. For this week's interview, we
have two different guests. First up is
John Keryaku. He is a former CI officer.
And he's going to help us sort out
what's the deal with Jeffrey Epstein
because the Trump administration wants
us to believe now there's nothing to see
here. Trump himself even said recently
that why are you guys asking me about
Jeffrey Epstein? It was Trump's own top
officials, including Dan Bonino, who's a
deputy head of the FBI, who were
constantly hyping up the Epstein files
as this huge massive cover up from the
deep state and Democrats. And once Trump
came to office, he was going to expose
it all. And now the Trump administration
is saying, "Hey, there's nothing to see
here."
>> And who better to talk about this with
us than John Kuryaku, who himself is a
major truth teller. He is a CIA
whistleblower. He's the only person to
have gone to prison over the CIA torture
program and he was a CIA analyst and
case officer. So, he has really great
insights into what could have happened
with these Epstein files and how uh the
CIA and other intelligence agencies are
fond of destroying evidence. And Katie
did this interview solo. So, let's go
now to Katie's interview with John
Kuryak.
[Applause]
Welcome back to the show, John Kuryaku.
>> Good to see you again.
>> You, too. It's always a pleasure. You're
an amazing storyteller uh and guest. And
uh we want to talk to you about Epstein.
>> Are you still talking about Jeffrey
Epstein? This guy's been talked about
for years. You're asking, "We have
Texas, we have this, we have all of the
things." And are people still talking
about this guy? this creep.
That is unbelievable.
Do you want to waste the time and do you
feel like answering?
>> I I don't mind answering.
>> I mean, I can't believe you're asking a
question on Epstein at a time like this
where we're having some of the greatest
success and and also tragedy with what
happened in Texas. It just seems uh like
a desecration. But you go ahead. How do
you like that?
>> Yeah. Big change from what he was saying
before.
>> We're going to get to the bottom of it.
said he's going to release all the
documents, the he's going to release the
videos and then you're still talking
about this,
>> right? Yeah. And he's hiding behind the
tragedy in Texas. Um, so what are your
thoughts? What what happened? I mean, I
I did see that on both uh Pierce Morgan
and on Fox News, you said that you feel
material was probably destroyed. Can you
elaborate on that and why that?
>> Sure. at the CIA.
Even though there are laws like the the
Federal Records Act, which specifically
says you cannot destroy documents,
they destroy documents all the time. I
mean MK Ultra even after even after
Congress specifically told the director
of central intelligence that he had to
preserve the MK Ultra documents, he went
back to headquarters and they destroyed
80% of the tens of thousands of pages of
documents that they had on MK Ultra. So
now, you know, we don't really know what
is true and what's not true about MK
Ultra because of of the cover up,
>> right? Same same thing at the CIA with
the torture videos. As soon as word
leaked out that there were videos of Abu
Zuba and Khalik Muhammad being tortured,
Harriet Meyers, who was the White House
counsel at the time in the in the George
uh W. Bush presidency, Harriet Meyer
specifically told Jose Rodriguez, the
deputy director for operations at the
CIA, and Gina Haspel, "Don't destroy the
tapes." And Gina Haspel put them in an
industrial grinder and destroyed them.
>> Right?
>> So, you know, why would we think that
the FBI would be any different,
especially when it comes to allegations
that some of the most powerful and some
of the wealthiest men in the world are
implicated in the scandal. Some of the
most powerful politicians in the world
may be implicated in this scandal,
right?
>> So, I could absolutely see the FBI
destroying documents. And we could
speculate as to what the reason would
be. It could be just cash on the
barrelhead.
>> You know, it may that may be it may be
as simple as that. It may be that
there's more to this so-called deep
state than people think there is. So
yeah, I I don't I don't trust that
just like like this revelation like oh
my goodness, it turns out there are no
documents, there are no dossas, there
are no videos except for child porn.
Come on, man. Going back to the 1990s
and you couldn't find anything.
>> Yeah, it's pretty implausible.
>> I don't buy it.
>> Right. I mean, it it is just one of the
latest examples of Trump and his
administration
uh promising to take things on, ranging
from, you know, the deep state to
draining the the swamp to uh the
industrial military-industrial complex
and then once they're in power, they
don't. Or being uh America firsters and
then saying ridiculous things about
Israel. I mean, everyone from Cash Patel
to Tammy Bruce making statements that
are embarrassingly
uh subordinate to Israel. So, I mean,
does this is this just because Trump is
really good at saying the right things?
He I mean, I always I always think of
him kind of like as a stand-up comedian.
Uh he he knows how to work a crowd. He
knows how to get a response from people.
Um but then in terms of actual policy,
he doesn't seem to to line up.
>> I think that he's really not terribly
interested in policy. I don't think he
ever has been. And certainly we've had
other presidents that weren't interested
in policy, but yeah, I think that he
says what happen whatever happens to be,
you know, at at the top of his mind and
um and whether he ends up contradicting
himself later or not, he doesn't really
care. I think that ideologically
he's a Zionist and I think he's so much
so that he's unwilling to bend. When I
was serving in Bahrain, the Amir of
Bahrain said something that has always
stuck in my mind. He said, "The last
American president to give the Arabs a
fair shake was George HW Bush."
>> Right?
>> And every president since then has just
been in the pay of the Israelis directly
or indirectly. And the Arabs don't even
pretend to think that they're going to
get a fair shake, but we're seeing it in
spades um in this administration.
>> Yeah, I it's interesting you said that
cuz I I think that Trump is and this is
why I thought there was like a very
small chance that he'd be better than
Biden because I think that Trump maybe
he's a Zionist, but I think his Zionism
is a lot less strong, a lot weaker than
uh Biden's. Like who was more in
generally I think Biden is more of an
ideologue than Trump. I mean, I think
Trump is pretty not, you know,
ideological, much more opportunistic.
>> Definitely a populist. Yep.
>> Yeah. I mean, full of it, but I think
just in general, you know, what the
bottom line for him is real estate uh
more than it is any any kind of
ideology. But, um, as someone who was in
the CIA, what did you observe about the
relationship between the United States
and Israel? Oh, more than any other
relationship that we have with any other
country in the world, the relationship
is dictated on Capitol Hill.
Not at the White House, but on Capitol
Hill. I I was I I was on a podcast
earlier today. We were talking about
this exact issue. And I said I said when
I when I went to the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee in 2009, I was the
senior investigator there working for
John Kerry. I had been in the job like a
day or two days and these lobbyists came
by. It was a parade of lobbyists, right?
Every cause, every lobbyist comes
through at one time or another, but this
this was the first group of lobbyists
and they came to the office and they
said, "Hey,
congratulations.
So great to have you on the Senate
Foreign Relations Committee. We're from
Apac and we want to bring you on an all
expenses paid trip to the Holy Land. I
was like, "Oh, thank you. No, no, thank
you."
Oh, we we have a tour already laid out.
We're going to take you to all the
Christians Christian holy sites and
you're going to see what a first world
country we are and we are America's
greatest ally and we're the only
democracy in the Middle East. I was
like, "No, thank you. Thank you." Well,
there were there were a bunch of people
who went. I didn't go. I I even was a
little bit rude and I said, "Look, if I
want to go to Israel, I'm going to pay
for my own trip to Israel, but I I don't
want you you guys to pay for a trip to
Israel." And I didn't go,
>> but others went. Well, it turns out they
do this with literally every staff for
every congressman, 435 of them in the
House and a hundred of them in the
Senate. That is money well spent. And
then they contribute millions upon
millions of dollars to um campaigns,
congressional campaigns mostly. And man,
if you look at Israel cockeyed, they'll
primary you,
>> right? And so they've gotten to the
point or they've gotten us to the point
where people are so afraid to say
anything about Israel, anything, because
if you say if if there's any criticism
at all, no matter how mild, even if the
criticism is of Benjamin Netanyahu as a
politician,
you're anti-Semitic. And then you've got
to dig yourself out of that hole.
>> Yeah. So most most elected officials
they they just don't want to deal with
it so they just go along.
>> And what can you tell us about the
relationship between Israeli and US
intelligence?
>> It is um not close on a uh on a personal
level. Uh we never liked Mossad. They
don't like us. Um the Israelis spy on
the United States and uh they deny and
deny and deny. In fact, I was on Pierce
Morgan a couple of weeks ago debating oh
my god Alan Dersowitz. I was with Scott
Horton and we were we were debating Alan
Dersowitz and uh Danny,
what was his name? Yalon, he was the
former head of Mossad general.
And I said
the Israeli spy on the United States and
he said no, no, no, that's not true.
when the Americans caught uh uh Jonathan
Pard in 1995, we stopped spying on the
United States. And I said, "With all due
respect, General, that's not true
because I didn't start at the CIA until
1990." and the chief of security warned
us that there were two uh Israeli
intelligence officers assigned to the
Israeli embassy in Washington and
187 undeclared Israeli intelligence
officers spread all across the United
States stealing American secrets after
having penetrated our defense
contractors. So, with all due respect,
you're dissembling here the Israeli spy
on the United States. What do you think
of the way that uh Trump has gone from
being America first to uh someone who is
a pretty sickopantic to BB? Now, to be
fair, it's a kind of circle jerk uh
where they both um really suck up to
each other. And of course, you have uh
Netanyahu, I mean, hilariously, uh
nominating Donald Trump for a Nobel
Peace
>> Nobel Peace Prize.
>> Yeah. Uh what do you think of this?
>> Well, circle jerk is the best way to say
it, actually.
I I won't get into the specifics of what
a circle jerk is. People can Google it.
But
>> when Trump dropped the fbomb, what was
it, a week ago, two weeks ago, that was
specifically meant for Netanyahu.
>> Okay?
>> Because Trump wanted his ceasefire
between the Israelis and the Iranians.
And Netanyahu was like, "Well, you know,
maybe we're going to launch one more.
Well, just one more barrage." And then
he's like, you know, cut it the [__] out
or whatever it was he said.
>> Yeah. They don't know what the [__]
they're doing. I think is what he said.
That was specifically meant for
Netanyahu because the Iranians only
react. They don't they don't proactively
attack Israel.
>> Right. Despite the way the media covers
it.
>> Correct. And so
that little there was just that little
blip for a day and then it was all
passed. I was driving um to Capitol Hill
last night. You couldn't turn left on on
17th Street. you couldn't turn left on
15th Street. Pennsylvania Avenue was
closed. I'm like, what the [__] is going
on here? Like, are they just going to
shut down the city? I said, why is it
like this? And the Uber driver said,
BB's in town. Nobody's moving anywhere
in Washington.
>> And then I I talked to a a a contact of
mine today who happens to be doing some
work for the Israeli embassy, and he
said that Netanyahu is staying for a
week. This isn't just an in-n-out visit
where he just meets with the president,
shake hands, does a photo op, and
leaves. He's here all week. That gives
you an idea of how close this
relationship is.
>> I think Netanyahu was sick and tired of
Joe Biden and the Democrats, even though
Biden and the Democrats gave them
literally everything they wanted, but
he's far more comfortable with Donald
Trump because I think he's able to manip
to manipulate Donald Trump.
>> I mean, maybe both of them, right?
Wasn't he able? Isn't that something?
Isn't that kind of like the bipartisan
uh a bipartisan phenomenon?
>> It really is. It really is. You know,
Katie, if I could add one thing, too.
Years ago, 2008 to 2012.
I'm I'm almost embarrassed to say this.
I was an adjunct professor of uh
intelligence studies at Liberty
University, which was Jerry Fwell's
evangelical Christian Yes. University.
to make it even worse in the Jesse Helm
School of Government.
>> Oh my gosh. Wow.
>> Okay. Yeah. And when they called me to
offer me this job, I said, "Why would
you guys call me?" I said, "We we
probably disagree on 99% of the issues.
Why me?" And without missing a beat, the
dean said, "Because torture is not
Christian."
>> Ah, interesting.
>> And I said, "Okay, I'll take it." And I
ended up really truly enjoying my time
there.
>> Nice guys. We disagreed on everything,
>> right?
>> But genuinely nice people.
>> I am still, for reasons that are unclear
to me, on the Liberty University list
served.
And every once in a while, I just can't
remain silent. And so I have to crack on
them.
They are so
what what word can I use? They are
so pro- Israel,
>> right,
>> as to be fanatical about it. And they
can't even explain to you why they're so
pro- Israel. I mean, deep down, I know
what it is. It's because they want all
the Jews to return to Israel so that the
Messiah can come and Armageddon and the
apocalypse and, you know, that whole
thing, which is all, you know, fantasy,
>> right? But um I crack on them all the
time and I say St. Borfidio's Church in
Gaza, the oldest continually operating
Christian church on earth.
And the Israelis bomb it to rubble and
kill everybody inside. By the way, every
one of them was either a woman or a
child. And you guys don't say anything
about that,
>> right? You don't say anything that
they're literally wiping out the
Palestinian Christian community in the
West Bank after having already wiped it
out in Gaza. You guys don't say a word.
But God forbid somebody should criticize
Benjamin Netanyahu. All of a sudden,
we're anti-Semitic.
>> I said, "You guys are anti-Christian
because you've literally not lifted a
finger to help Palestine's Christians.
Christians who have been there for 2,000
years.
2,000 years. You don't say a word about
that. And then nobody says anything.
>> Yeah. And of course, uh it's also not
very Christian to support genocide.
>> No.
>> And it's also not very pro I mean, we
know this as you said, it's it's totally
opportunistic and transactional. Uh they
they are not friends of the Jews. I mean
that utilize us and like you mentioned.
So we'll all go back. I think 400 of us
get to survive and the rest burn for all
eternity.
>> That's exactly right. That Yeah, they
make it seem like in fact, you know
what? There was a scene in the Sopranos
about exactly that. That what that
somebody said, well, they're great
friends of Israel. And then Hesh said,
"Oh, don't let that fool you. They only
like Israel because they want us to all
go back there so they can kill us all."
>> Wow.
>> And that's really what it comes down to.
>> I did not know that. I'm going to have
to watch that now. Yeah. So, on Fox News
um with Marie Bartomo, Netanyahu made
some comments about how he has quote
broken the Iran access end quote and
helped usher in a new Middle East. What
are your reactions to this claim? As
someone who has worked extensively in
the region and written about Iran
before, is there any uh validity to his
claims?
>> I hate to say yes. Um, I think it's
temporary because people aren't stupid
and the world is constantly changing and
so the Iranians and the Lebanese and
probably the Palestinians will figure
something out. But if you look at just
the last 6 months,
well the last eight months, he
decapitated Hzbalah.
Decapitated it for for all intents and
purposes. It's it it has ceased to
exist. It's going to come back.
>> Yeah.
>> But right now it's it's nothing.
>> He essentially working with the Turks
overthrew Bashar al-Assad.
>> I'm no supporter of Bashar al-Assad, but
but I always said
if you're concerned about Christian
communities, Bashar al-Assad was the
only thing standing between the
Christian communities and complete
annihilation.
>> Yeah.
Uh, so Assad's gone, too. And Gaza's
been just, you know, vaporized. It's
almost, it's almost gone in and of
itself. So, for the time being, yeah,
he's broken the Iranian access. He still
has the Houthies to worry about, but
they're more of a little, you know,
pimple on the butt of the Israeli body
politic than they are a real threat to
anything. And I wouldn't be surprised if
they start, you know, bombarding the
Houthies. But the Houthies are so poor
and they have so little. I mean, how
many million dollar bombs are you going
to spend to blow up $10,000 drones?
Really, is it worth it?
>> Um, when when the Israelis
u implemented this operation against
Hezbollah with the pagers, the pagers
and the cell phones.
>> My phone ran off rang off the hook with
former agency friends like, "What do you
think about this?" And I said, "Holy
[__] this is like on the one hand, it's
a it's a crime against humanity or a war
crime, depending on your your position."
Clearly, innocent civilians, including
children, were hurt or killed because
these things just arbitrarily blew up.
And, you know, we saw reports of people
having taken their phones out of their
pockets and they put it on the table so
they could have dinner with their
families and it blew up and killed the
nine-year-old girl
>> that it was next to.
So yeah, war crime,
but absolutely brilliant from an
intelligence operations perspective.
Imagine the moving parts that went into
an operation like this where you've got
to control literally everything from the
point of manufacturing
through the supply chain across half the
globe and then into the hands of the
consumer.
Absolutely incredible. I don't know if
we'll ever be able to figure out how
they pulled this off,
>> right?
>> And then, you know, working with the
Turks, who the Israelis either love or
hate, depending on what day of the week
it happens to be, they came to this
agreement that if you help us screw
Assad, we'll help you screw the Kurds.
And the Turks said, "Sounds good to us."
Next thing you know, the Assad family
runs off to Moscow. Bashar comes back
for a week, fills the plane with riches,
and then he runs off to Moscow.
>> Right.
>> So, these the Israelis have been very
busy, and they've been very successful
at it. For better or for worse,
>> for worse, I would say. Um,
>> but, you know, it's interesting because
you have some people who say, "Oh, that
was not I mean, obviously there's
there's a lot of people say it's
technically technologically brilliant."
But then you have people saying, "Oh, it
was targeted. It wasn't targeted at
all." as you just pointed out, it killed
it.
>> Wasn't targeted.
>> Yeah. And um you know, Leon Petta, who's
not exactly a peace, he said it was an
act of terrorism.
>> Yeah. I that that shocked me because I
would have expected the likes of Leon
Petta to say, you know, bravo Mossad. Oh
my god, we should all aspire to do
things like that. But even he said it
was an act of terrorism, which it was,
>> right?
>> It was. So going back to uh Epstein,
what is the relationship between Epstein
and Israel? And what do we know about uh
who was uh on the plane uh who engaged
in, you know, basically sex crimes.
>> And to hear the rest of the interview,
please go to useful idiotsspodcast.com.
>> And to hear the full interview with
John, please go to
usefulidiotsspodcast.com.
Uh, and it's a great it's a great uh
interview. I really got to say always
love talking to him.
>> All right, up next we have a returning
guest who's I spoke to Marta Havsko. Uh,
she is visiting assistant professor at
the Straler Center for Holocaust
Genocide Studies at Clark University and
we talked to her about the ongoing proxy
war in Ukraine which is not coming to an
end despite Trump's promises to uh
broker a peace deal within 24 hours.
He's now been in office for uh I don't
know almost half a year and this war is
ongoing and it's not going well for
everybody especially Ukrainians as we
will hear now from our guest Marta
Havsko.
[Applause]
>> Marta Havishko, thank you so much for
coming back to useful idiots.
>> Thanks for having me.
>> It's been a while since we covered uh
Ukraine on the show. So I just want to
start by asking you what is going on for
people who are not following the
day-to-day of the conflict. What do you
think is most important for people to
understand about the current situation
inside Ukraine?
>> So the current situation is very dire um
due to different uh different
developments. First of all severe
Russian attacks. Now uh it was a new
record when Russia during one night sent
more than 700 drones across Ukraine to
attack different Ukraine cities and to
attack Ukraine infrastructure
infrastructure and of course um we have
the damage of residential buildings as
well and deaths and injuries of civilian
people including including children. So
basically war is one of the most
important factor but the second factor
and according to some polls it's even
more um it's even bigger trouble for
some Ukraine is a corruption
almost every single day we have new
corruption scandals for example the
deputy prime minister
who recently had um business travel
abroad and some some journalists assume
that he escaped from Ukraine Ukraine
because he was accused of corruption.
And this is huge corruption scandal
because the damage to Ukraine to Ukraine
budget was approximately 1 billion
grievas.
And guess what? Ukraine court just you
know just release him without you know
fire him and with um you know this bail
that is very small in comparison to
damage to Ukraine government every
single day
Ukraine people see how you know top
politicians members of parliament
members of government and their their
relatives buy new cars, buy new
apartment in Ukraine and abroad in US
and in Europe. But every single day the
same ordinary citizens are um required
to donate for the army to buy necessary
stuff even to buy weapon. So basically
this situation the corruption still one
of the biggest problem in Ukraine. And
recently Ukraine Ukraine people found
out that many prominent journalists they
basically are um cooperating with
security service of Ukraine and with
military intelligence of Ukraine. But at
the same time they label themselves as
you know independent journalists,
investigative journalists. So basically
it's a total distrust nowadays in
Ukraine in the whole you know
governmental system and many people
don't believe that you know Zilinski
team is handling the whole situation
very good because we we observe this you
know clash the this disaster at the oval
office after that you know Zilinsky had
several meetings with Trump and drop
said oh it was a good conversation but
still despite of this good conversation
we observe how Trump hold um uh
delivering a weapon to Ukraine. So
basically the situation is very dire and
um nobody understand what is the plan
how to defeat Russia, how to regain lost
territories with the enormous amount of
desertters from Ukraine army and numbers
are different according to different
sources but at least 200,000 people
deserted from Ukraine army. So the lack
on the infantry people, the lack of
soldiers, the lack of weapon, the lack
of you know these these sufficient
support from the west because we observe
even neighboring Poland people are tired
of this war and many of them don't want
only approximately 15% of Polish people
want to send their sons their husbands
to Ukraine to fight Russians. So
basically no one wants to send their
their uh their loved ones to die for
Ukraine for this corrupted government
for this you know ethnationalist
you know politics and uh with
neighboring countries you know Poland,
Hungary, Romania we have so many you
know tensions in regard to you know
language question and other uh questions
in humanitarian politics. So Ukraine
people are uh frustrated many of Ukraine
people and they don't see the light in
the tunnel. What next? Mers talked about
you know towers for Ukraine. we will
support as um long as as it as it took.
But now the days what we observe pause
in delivering weapons blah blah blah
many talks and um you know uh only you
know small small baby steps and in this
configuration Ukraine has no chances to
regain lost territories. Those who
observe closely how many territories
Ukraine is losing every single day, it's
at least 15 20 square kilometers per
day. And you know those scandals with
with the lack of, you know, uh these uh
uh infrastructure that could hold this
Russian offensive, you know. So people
asking what have you you know done for
for you know strengthening Ukrainian
defense system why where are those money
you talked about this all the time you
invaded Kursk and you explain Korsk
region in Russia and you explain to
ordinary people that this was such a
great operation and so now Russians are
retaliating because they want to at
least create this zone security zone and
prevent another attack of Korsk region
of Belgarat region. And so even Billeski
this you know celebrity of commander
when he was asked about K corporation he
said oh at the beginning it was a good
you know result because it boosts morale
of Ukrainians you know and humiliate um
and humiliate Putin and his generals.
Yeah. But what happened next? we will
talk about this you know history will
judge. So he avoided even to express his
criticism of this operation and the many
many you know commanders are very
critical of this operation. So basically
the main I believe the main main mood in
Ukraine is disappointment.
um regardless of these cheering uh
comments from from you know state
control media that are trying you know
to to to talk about resilience and you
know those uh Ukraans who want to rather
die um experience glorious death for
other Ukraine than you know raise their
children you know in in peacefully. So
it's it's insane.
>> Let me show you a headline from a
Ukrainian outlet. Uh that speaks to the
long-term problems that Ukraine faces
now on top of the immediate. Uh this is
what it said. Ukraine has already lost
40% of its working age population
according to the Ministry of Social
Policy which also says that to restore
the economy, Ukraine needs to attract an
additional 4 to 5 million workers. Talk
to us about this and um you know what
this means for the country's future.
>> Exactly. you know when when people those
in the west who are I call them you know
keyboard warriors who are you know just
cheering waving Ukraine flags you know
put on their social media you know
Ukraine flags and stand with with
Ukraine Slava Ukraine Ukraini and be
brave as Ukraine they just you know they
watch this you know as a video game they
really you know for them it's very
interesting all these developments how
you know people to to observe how people
are dying, you know, on the battlefield
and how they are persecuted by drones.
But war is not only the battlefield.
Battlefield is most visible. Combat is
most visible. Yes, we talked about
different numbers about wounded soldiers
about soldiers without limbs uh you know
about um missing soldiers, soldiers
about killed soldiers but war basically
has so many dimensions
and man one of these dimensions
connected to this situation with work
force. Ukraine experience enormous lack
of work force and nowadays Ukraine
officials are talking about inviting
people from from Argentina, Colombia,
Bangladesh and other countries. And this
discussion is very tense. Why? because
they uh many people consider this
question in terms of this anti-immigrant
rhetoric anti-Muslim rhetoric that is on
the rise in the west and due to this
rhetoric many farright in different
countries including Germany Austria you
know Sweden other countries France gain
so um gain popularity and many
especially far right they are so
concerned because they are saying you
White men are dying in the battlefield
and what will happen next? They will
bring you know brown people, black
people, not Christian people. So they
consider this as a security threat for
Ukraine. So there is no a good solution
for this and as long as war will
continue the more people will leave
Ukraine. Even today I have so many of my
acquaint acquaintances and friends and
relatives who consider to take their
sons abroad before they turn 18
just in order to to give them better
perspectives and in order to spare them
from these force mobilization in order
to give them a future basically at least
some future because what Ukraine
proposed Ukraine officially officials
constantly say you should prepare for
long war. You should prepare basically
for forever war. So what next? You know
people can't understand what is the
plan. And more and more people I mean
not only women who face no restrictions
in movement. I mean men are paying tens
of thousand of euros and dollars just to
escape Ukraine. They use different ways,
you know, they they they pretend to be,
you know, volunteers, they pretend to be
musicians, they pretend to visit, you
know, some conferences abroad and then
they never return to Ukraine. So they
pay for this, you know, for for these
excuses or they um they are hired by
some, you know, politicians as their
drivers and they just escape Ukraine.
You know, I was so shocked when, you
know, uh I I left Ukraine as some of our
reviewers maybe know. I escaped Ukraine
almost immediately after Russian um
Russian attack in February 2022.
But I often visit Europe for different
academic events, academic conferences.
So basically in 2022 when I visited, you
know, Czech Republic in Germany, most uh
of Ukraine refugees were women and
children. Year after that in 2023,
many of Ukraine refugees and they hear
Ukraine, Ukraine Russian language and
Ukraine language were men. They are
there were young men of the draft age
with their families with small children.
So many men basically are very open
about this. If you want forever war,
send your children. Why your children
are here? Why you know a son of the
ex-president of Ukraine Prohenko is
avoiding draft and ignores draft you
know messages and he's living his luxury
life in Great Britain. Why Klitschko
sansa in Germany? Why so many
politicians have their sons here in US
where the uh you know education is so
expensive? I, you know, teach um I teach
at Clark University and I observe it's
enormous prices for Ukraine people. The
average salary, monthly salary in
Ukraine is approximately $600,
but we all know how much Ukraine Ukraine
officials pay for the education of their
children here. And you know many of them
are politicians without business
involvement without any business without
any commercial activity. So basically
they they just stole this you know these
money these funds from Ukraine budget
allegedly and their sansa are you know
so basically what we observe now rich
people in Ukraine getting more rich due
to the war and you know different
schemes and poor people became even more
poor because they can't pay the bribe to
avoid force conscription
>> they are sent directly to the infantry
and to the most heavy battles.
>> The last time we had you on the show, we
played footage of, you know, just some
of the basically kidnappings of people
uh being taken off the street to go be
enlisted to be forced to to fight. And
recently, Russia has been bombing some
of these Ukrainian recruitment centers.
And there have been like reports of some
Ukrainians on social media basically
cheering this on because these
recruitment centers are seen as the
symbol of tyranny, forcing people to go
off to die. who don't want to. Now, I
want to read you something though from
the Washington Post in reporting on
this. This is what this is what the
Washington Post says about the issue of
military recruitment uh inside Ukraine.
There is a great deal of Russian
sponsored content and propaganda on
social media maintaining that Ukraine
engages in highly unpopular forced
recruitment of its citizens. So, that's
the Washington Post. I mean, is this
just Russian propaganda that uh Ukraine
is setting people off to die and
engaging in un what it calls unpopular
force recruitment? Actually, you know,
of course, Russia instrumentalizes this,
you know, this tension, this anger, this
frustration because military draft
officers, recruitment draft officers in
Ukraine are associated with
dictatorship, are associated with the
profession of basic human rights. And u
many people can't understand why they
should die for this corrupted state, why
they should die for autocracy.
um because Ukraine is on its way to
dictatorship because you know many signs
and we can talk we can talk about this
later. So basically yes Russians are
trying to instigate this anger. They are
trying to support these people but it's
not only you know it's not only Russian
propaganda and some Russian trolls paid
trolls. Why I am saying this? Because
because after this you know strikes on
several recruitment center inava
many people when you witness on social
media um um how people comment on this
it was you know it it was a humilation
for Ukraine government and for military
commanders that's why it was even an
appeal of command of ground forces
published in mainstream, one of the
mainstream Ukraine media, Ukraine,
Ukraine. It was appealed to the people,
please stop. Those people are your
defenders. They are part of Ukraine
military of Ukraine armory that defends
you from Russian, you know, [__] orcs
and all this stuff. You should support
them, not to cheer their deaths and, you
know, those wounded soldiers who were
inside. And so many celebrity
commanders, military commanders who are
very present on the media, they pause
their, you know, outrageous pause. How
dare you? We defend you. Stop laughing.
Stop be happy about this. And security
service of Ukraine started to trace all
those comments. And yesterday, one man
already was interrogated. and they make
sure that the this information will be
leaked to the press in order to give a
lesson to other people. Please stop
doing that or you will face punishment.
And we know recently UN released report
about the human rights in Ukraine and
they uh were and um there is a great
skepticism about the punishment for
so-called collaboration. So that
collaboration is such a broader uh such
a broad definition in Ukraine that
dozens of people are put um put on trial
and charged with treason for comments on
social media like this like cheering
this attacks on recruitment centers. So
basically nowadays everyone who is
critical about you know for example
personal sanctions against you know
Ukraine imposed by Zilinski against his
critics or is not happy about beatings
kidnappings and killings of people in
territorial recruitment centers they
could be blamed for spreading so-called
Russian propaganda to be the paid
Russian assets and of treason. So
basically nowadays martial law gives a
lot of you know free hand to security
service and to all these law enforcement
that use even draft military draft
selective military draft as a punishment
against you know human rights activists.
Yesterday, one of the journalists who
was, you know, who was um um highly
advocating um these of you know draft
officers, violent deeds, he was drafted.
Why? Because he criticized the
government and you know people say why
why you doing that? So basically they uh
the government is sending a signal to
all those critics. You can be on his
place. You can be drafted easily you
know and sent to the front line to the
very hell and guess what what will
happen to you you know and um uh uh uh
what I must say regarding um um
territorial recruitment centers. I
invite our listeners and viewers to
check uh the um latest uh Victor Orban
post with condolences to one of their
men 45 years old from uh Transcarpatia.
It's a Ukraine region and this guy um
had both Ukraine and Hungarian
citizenship and he experienced force
mobilization and he was so severely
beaten that he died three weeks later.
So basically those stories are almost
absent in western media because they
don't want to undermine these force
mobilization. Yes. Because they they
many of of Yes. Yes. Thank you so much.
>> We're showing his picture on screen for
our audience.
>> His sister shared uh the news about him
and all the details about about him. And
he's not the first victim. We know so
many little cases in different regions
of Ukraine. Recently the guy from uh he
was basically his father, he was a
combat volunteer. his father was
proclaimed missing on the battlefield
one year ago in Pocro somewhere uh in in
Pocross region. So he should be exempted
from the military but he was attacked by
draft officers. He was beaten allegedly
and he died also. He died he was 31 year
old. So only in the past years we found
out two cases of deaths of those who
experienced force mobilization and we
all understand that during martial law
many people in Ukraine are not willing
to expose this information to make it
public because the trust to law
enforcement in Ukraine is approximately
you know 10%
nobody because of the extreme corruption
in this judicial system in the police
system. Nobody trusts the government but
they really believe that they can face
retaliation from the government. They
can lose their you know jobs for the
criticism and exposing this information.
They can be drafted to the military or
their relatives uh can face
repercussions. So basically it's only
the top of the iceberg that we observe
you know but many people many people
experienced in Ukraine this you know
beating because why the one of the
reason because draft officers were given
free hands because commanders soldiers
experts they say in one voice
infantry we need infantry we running out
of soldiers and nobody wants to go there
you know I observe you know the
thousands of NAF fellas on the internet.
These brave, you know, archair warriors
and nobody wants to go to Ukraine
infantry. Nobody wants to experience,
you know, chasing by Russian drone.
Nobody wants to to live their rest life
without, you know, limbs, without, you
know, penis or without, you know, eyes.
So it it's you know it's obvious that
for many people it's a you know it's
just game when real people are dying in
Ukraine.
>> Let's talk about one of the Zenfi
government's uh more recent and
controversial appointments. Ukraine has
something called the Institute of
National Memory. It's basically a
history division of the government and
they've just appointed uh this man to
head it. Uh let's show him on screen.
His name is Alexander Alfarov.
>> Aurorov Alurov. It's a very Russian name
actually.
>> Well, so talk to us about who he is.
Talk to us about who he is.
>> So basically uh Alexandra Alurov is a
historian
is a PhD. So he's basically was trained
as as a historian. He's a he's a scholar
in Ukraine. He has a very popular blog
in Ukraine about Ukraine history and
many of these you know uh his TV shows
are dedicated you know um I would say to
demonization and diversification of
Ukraine history you know so basically
all this stuff but what is more
important Alexandra Alfuro was a press
officer of Azo regiment in 2014 2015
when this regiment was accused for so
many war crimes in Donbas region. And
when members of this regiment were very
open about their neo-Nazis and making
Nazi salutes very openly and they were
very open extremist.
After that when after 2022 he joined the
special operation forces avoc
assault brigade responsible for
humanitarian question and you know
ideological question. So basically for
theological train of young men who are
recruited who are lured to the army. So
basically he's telling them that
glorious death for Ukraine is the best
option for you you know and you will be
celebrated as hero. to go, you know, and
enlist and and you know, experience
this, you know, great glory. But what is
important about Alfuro as well as well
the third assault brigade in 2023 in one
of the biggest museum in cave organized
um photo exhibition
uh that showed three at least three
photos of Vafeness's division Galatia.
It was the collaborationist Nazi
military formation that um keep oath to
Hitler and fight for Nazi Germany and
committed war crimes in Slovakia for
Yugoslavia and other regions. Some of
the participants of these weapons as
division Galatia participated in uh uh
oppression of wars uprising in punitive
operation against Polish people in Guta
Pyanska and other and other cities. uh
in the territory of Ukraine and Poland
and Belarus and and and others and many
of them actually were members of
auxilary police. So basically they were
involved in the Holocaust. So this guy
actually created this exhibition and
guess what members of his his brothers
in arm members of his assel brigade they
reenacted these fathers. So basically
they compare themselves to Nazi
collaborators not Putin not Scaba not
Solio or other top Kremlin propagandists
they themselves and this exhibition was
created by Alfuro and guess what
recently when he was appointed many
people started to to talk about his you
know background about his youth and we
found an interview recorded last year
when he praised is Hitler. He compared
Hitler to Putin and say, "Oh, no, no,
no. We can't compare those figures
because Hitler, he received high German
education. He was acquainted with high
German philosophy and music. He, you
know, so basically he advocated Hitler."
And then you know uh I listen to this
interview and as a holocaust scholar as
a you know person who teach Holocaust
I'm a Holocaust educator no and I
listened how he started to defend uh you
know he said you know Russians are
trying to develop this myth that all
Ukraines are anti-semmites and guess
what during the period of Ukrainian
people's republic proclaimed In 1918 it
was you know se separate state from from
Russia for the first you know time in
20th century. They even organized the
ministry of Jewish affairs and they have
the banknotes with Yiddish and it was
true but then he stopped. But what
happened next? The wave of anti-Jewish
programs perpetrated by the army of
these republics and tens of thousands of
Jews were killed were wounded were
robbed and were raped and it caused one
of the biggest wave of immigration to
United States. I have so many students,
my students here at Clark Universities
whose relatives came as a result of
these programs. We know that many actors
perpetrated those programs including you
know white army bel and even some you
know parts of the Soviet army but the
most programs were perpetrated by those
you know Ukraine nationalists you know
but this Ukraine army army of Ukraine
independent state but he's saying
nothing about this so what to expect
from this guy on this you know and I
must say this is the main national
memory actor in Ukraine Ukraine it's a
governmental institution and we know
that at least 50% of Ukraine budget
is uh filled by by you know western
countries and all salaries of all
government workers are paid by western
pay taxpayers. So I want to ask those
Hulk scholars, Hulk descendants, Hulk
survivors, are you ready to pay him
salary? Do you want him on the top of
this, you know, institution in charge of
creating national memory in Ukraine?
>> You know, it's a shame.
>> These are questions. These are questions
that I wish our media asked, but
unfortunately still not allowed to be
discussed in the mainstream. We're going
to wrap. Martin, so you said earlier
that, you know, you're worrying that
Ukraine is becoming a dictatorship. Is
there any aspect of this they haven't
discussed yet in our conversation that
you want to make sure we address before
we wrap?
>> Um, I want to to um address the question
of so-called personal sanctions imposed
by directly by Zalinski.
So in past weeks and months, Zalinski by
his personal decision uh decisions
imposed personal sanctions against some
politicians, journalists and bloggers.
Most of them of course escaped from
Ukraine, including Arestovich, his
former advisor who is very critical of
what is going on in Ukraine nowadays.
And this list is very wide and includes
you know people uh like you know
Bundareno who um wrote this book Joker
uh very critical towards Zilinski. So
basically
uh many human rights organization
organizations even in Ukraine
and uh uh and recently the council of
Europe commission for human rights they
paid attention for this and they are
very critical of this because it's
against those sanctions are against
constitution because in order to impose
sanctions you need to prove that those
people are involved in some terrorist
activity or horror and this must be
proved in the court. But what Zilinski
did, he did this against you know all
Ukraine laws and it violates not only
Ukraine constitution and Ukraine laws
but also those laws and uh international
treaties signed by Ukraine. So basically
those who say oh Ukraine is such a
vibrant democracy. No guys, you know,
no. And what we observe many media in
Ukraine who were fin which were financed
by USA and pretended to be you know
liberal independent you know media. Now
they join this you know bullying of
these people sanctioned by Zalinski.
They justify this to the public. They
use slurs against those people, strong
wars. But the only you know their fault
is the harsh criticism of Zalinski and
his team and the corruption and how they
handle the war and how you know they
protect the children of their own you
know bodies from the front because in
Ukraine military draft is very selective
and targets you know and it's used as a
punitive instrument against dissident
you know against some politicians. We
know that Porrohenko is sanctioned
nowadays. He can't freely, you know,
visit some, you know, meet with some
politicians abroad. So basically what we
observe now, it has nothing to do with
democracy. And if Zalinski will keep his
power,
I believe Ukraine will be rapidly turned
into authoritarian state. But in the
west, we have complete silence and
justification because our Ukraine are
fighting for it's an existential war.
Yes, it is existential war for Zilinski
regime and for his bodies because war
secure their what secures their
political influence and their political
power because
>> and for us it's a proxy war that is
being used to bleed a rival Russia.
>> Exactly. And many you know many western
politicians are so open about this.
Yeah. German commanders, you know, we
want to keep Ukraine fighting at least
until 2030 because we should prepare, we
should rearm. So, how many Ukraine
should die to protect Europe from, you
know, from Russia and to satisfy the
needs of, you know, those wararm mongers
in the west.
>> Another question that's just not being
posed enough. Uh, it's in fact not being
posed at all in the mainstream. And if
we had a functioning democracy, it
would. Marta, it takes a lot of courage
to speak out the way you have. We're
very grateful to you for joining us and
sharing your insight. Marta Havishko,
visiting assistant professor at the
Straler Center for Holocaust and
Genocide Studies at Clark University.
Thanks so much.
>> Thank you.
[Applause]
>> And thank you again so much to Marta
Havisho. And previously we heard from
John Keryaku. And again, for the full
interview with John Kyaku, go and sign
up to be a subscriber at
usefulpodcast.com.
>> And also, Marta has such an important
voice, so always glad to hear from her.
>> That's our show. Thanks so much for
tuning in. We'll see you next time.
>> Bye, everyone.
>> Thanks so much for listening to and
watching Useful Idiots. For extended
episodes, bonus content, and our weekly
Thursday throwdown episode, please
subscribe at usefulspodcast.com.
Support the show for free by subscribing
on YouTube, Rumble, and wherever you get
your podcast. And if you like the
podcast, don't forget to rate and
review. You can also follow us on
Twitter at useful idiotpod. Thanks for
supporting Independent Media. We'll see
you next time.
[Music]